Okay, we are going to call to order this regular meeting of the City Council for today's
date.
Item two is, public hearing on proposed FY-2016-2017 budget.
Public hearing is called for any member of the public to present to the governing body
and the comments recommendations, information on any part of the proposed budget.
Anyone that wants to address the council on the proposed budget?
They're being, no, we're going to move on to item three, which is public input and unscheduled
personal affairs.
They want to relate to what's just to address the council on any of the agenda items.
They're being non-edum fours, consent agenda, stamp is recommending items five to fifteen
for the consent agenda.
You know, is there one item that you want to pull out?
Yeah, there's item twelve, if there's no other objection, I'll make a motion to prove items
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 13, 14, 15.
Okay, do we have a second?
Second, roll call, please.
Johnson?
Aye.
Western?
Four of string?
Aye.
Lewis?
Neil, if you want to elaborate on twelve?
Yeah, I just want to make sure everybody's aware that this amended calendar for our council meeting.
The only one that is affected is the fourth to the area of our, which is our work shop.
It's not our regular first and third to the side.
That's the only one that has changed.
So, and we just changed the time.
Just changed the time from five to thirty to four.
To four.
So, the workshop meetings that are the last two, not always last Tuesday, four, two, the
year of the month.
The time on that's been moved up from five to three to four, clock the start, time.
Anything else?
No, I'll put that on my commotion to prove out in the twill.
Okay, yeah, I'll second that, roll call, please.
Johnson?
Schultz?
Aye.
Western?
Lewis?
Sir routine?
15?
16.
I hear 17.
What?
We have to work.
I knew Tyler was walking up.
I was trying to figure out why.
Item 16, early project development packet for my annual regional airport.
Tyler?
Yes, sir.
This is, we're asking for approval tonight for the early project development packet to submit to the
FAA.
This is for design only.
This is for the lighting and a raw system, papies, odals, in the navids, so they help guide
the pilots in, help give them the correct angles, different things like that.
So, it's a really, really neat deal for airport, I mean a lot of people that fly in from, for
example, to come to Newl, they ask, well, why don't you guys have an A-wasse, why don't you
guys have this?
So, it's kind of a really, and it's termed only project development just because we're early
in the process.
Yes, sir.
So, what we'll do is, when you guys are pretty distant tonight, we will send this to
you.
And they will put it in their queue to get funding for it.
So according to them, we already have the grant that just need to get us in the queue to get funding started.
So the financial commitment on this is 19,320, which we do have in the budget that we ask you to approve for any type of the grant program like this.
We are responsible for 10% of it.
We plan on having this out of airport revenues.
And again, a project like this is going to be very important because once we have systems like this,
we'll have more people flying in, more revenue at the airport.
It's really important for the airport growth.
So Chuck and and Tyler have done a really good job on this project.
Okay.
So we just need a motion to approve, correct?
Yes, sir.
I'll make that motion to do a half a second.
That's the kind of roll call.
Schultz, Lewis, I forster, Western, Johnson.
All right.
Thank you.
I'm 17.
Okay.
All four permit and MS4 program of day.
Todd, how are you tonight?
That's great.
Good job with you.
I've got Bobby Joe with me.
All right.
Todd, Bobby Joe, can I do a quick introduction?
Because you are an added number of the meetings, but there have been some of our budget meetings
that there are some questions being asked about our regulations on stormwater.
And thought that before we get into the budget that Todd and Bobby Joe can talk about basically what we do
under, what we call our MS4, some of the regulations that we have to adhere to.
And just bringing you up to speed, I think a lot of you have really not been exposed to what
we have to do here.
And I got a very quick update because when I was serving in Branson, we suddenly went under the
MS4 regulations.
So we had to get a kicked off in a city like Branson, which was very interesting.
So another Todd and Bobby Joe has done a terrific job on what we're supposed to do, just wanted
to give you an update on it.
Okay.
And on that, the reason we're both here is because when we originally was thinking about doing
this update, we were thinking stormwater program, but I wanted to update you on the permits
because there's actually three different stormwater permits.
And then Bobby, she wrote the program for the stormwater, so I'm going to let her do that part of it.
But first we have the OKR4, which is actually our MS4, which is an inescal separate storm
system.
So it kind of covers all the stormgradings, ditches, and pipes that take the stormwater
to the rivers and the creeks, and she'll get more detail in that a minute.
And then we have the OKR5, that covers industrial stormwater discharge.
And what that is is EPA made, when they did this stormwater, they made a list of industries.
And if your municipality has a stormwater permit and has these industries in your municipality,
then they must have their own stormwater pollution prevention plan.
And actually they have their own permit.
We have three of them.
first station, the white square treatment plant and the airport. Some of the thing a couple
of requirements we do and I was who have to do monthly inspections for pollution prevention
and then we do monitoring of our outfalls and then every year at the end of the year we have
to turn in what they call an ACER report and I'm going to read that because I never can't remember
what it is but I gotta get my glasses on. It's actually an annual comprehensive site compliance
evaluation report so that has to be turned in every year and then we have the okay R10 that
covers stormwater drainage from construction sites. So how that works is if if a contractor wants
to come in and build something that disturbs an ACER or more ground they have to submit a
pollution prevention plan and a soil and erosion control plan to DQ and get a permit.
The other part of that is if you have a construction site inside a
sensitive water body the permit wanted us to do something more stringent.
The Ocial Rivers of sensitive water body it's on the 303D list for impaired water bodies. That's
303D list is I list of all the streams and rivers that are impaired for some reason or another.
The Ocial Rivers is impaired for TSS total suspended solids. So what we elected to do was
downsize that to a half acre more but those permits I can do they don't have to go through DQ.
And then like to point out one more thing about the stormwater permits because they're so different
like the wastewater plant when I get a permit for it it kind of tells you what you gotta do
and what testing you're going to do what you gotta meet and you just follow it. But the stormwater
permits they're written where you have to write a program to meet those requirements and send that to
DQ and get it approved. And Bobby Bobby just got through writing what I think we turned that in and what
anywhere. January. January and we're waiting for a result from that still so all that heard
we're talking about that part. Okay well basically back in 1999 EPA decided that
a quality of water was deteriorating and of course it's that's water sustains life of all all from
kinds. And you put your mind down so not as tall as Todd. Okay so anyway EPA in at 99 said
we've gotta do something we gotta try to clean up our waters and so they came up with what's called
the phase two stormwater regulations that's creating a permit when they did that the state of Oklahoma.
We requested to be our regulatory agency.
So we don't answer to EPA, we answer to ODEQ.
And it took ODEQ five years past EPA coming up with the program.
For them to come up with the permit to make anybody that has 10,000 population up to 100,000
by this permit.
So our first permit for five years, five year permit, passed in 2005.
And it expired 2010.
However, it took ODEQ five more years to re-issue the second one.
So that one just passed here in October 1st of this year, became affected November 1st.
And it will expire on the 2020 October 31st.
But this permit as Todd said, there's regulations that EPA says needs to happen.
DEQ has put it in a permit and told us, these are the things you need to do.
Now you need to tell me how you're going to do that.
So then we have to come up with a stormwater management program.
It's called an SWMP and it's rather large.
And so a lot of it, a lot of the things you have no choice, they, you're only option is how
you choose to come up with their end result.
So basically this year, the new things that they wrote in the permit are the only things that
really need to be addressed because we've already addressed the others.
We just need to keep going on with them.
What the requirements are for this permit is that there's six minimum control measures that
DEQ wants us to try to prevent pollution.
And one way is with public education.
So the minimum control measure number two is involving the public.
MCM3, a list at discharge, elimination and detection, basically illegal dumping.
MCM4, construction, we have to control erosion and pollution from construction sites.
Post construction is the biggie for this new permit.
It's huge, low impact development.
In pervious, they don't want impervious anymore.
They want most everything.
You know, still at the water can soak in.
instead of going to the to the river. And the last one is the basic pollution prevention
and good housekeeping. And that's that's for us, municipality, basically, to make sure that
all of our facilities are doing what they can do to help control the pollution. I don't know,
a lot of people don't realize that it is a total different infrastructure. So anything that goes
into an intake or anything like that, anything that rains within the city limits is going to
go into the Nio Show without getting treated. So whatever pollution is out there, somebody
spilled some oil, somebody washed their car on the street, grass clippings, all that, is eventually
going straight to the river and causing a worse problem with our condition of our 303D
and TAR Creek as well. So for those minimum control measures, I derived a program
the storm water management program and address each one of those six MCMs using best management practices
and what they BMPs. What I had to do was tell them, if I'm going to have to work on MCM1 public education,
here's how I'm going to do it. I'm going to hand out brochures. I'm going to use the city website that
kind of thing. And LIA have to report to them. Let them know and quantify what I've done when I've done it
and that's just about as big as the actual storm water program at Selfie Gem and it will report.
We have, the collectively this year for this second five year permit, we have approximately 80
BMPs that cover all of the six MCMs, minimum control measures. And then we have to do that. It's
called MEP to the maximum extent practical. As long as we can prove that, then we stay in compliance
basically. So we haven't heard back yet from our notice of intent, the end our storm water permit that we just
wrote. So we don't know if it's been denied, it'll be approved. We haven't heard yet, but it has been paid for.
So maybe that's why they're not in hurry. But anyway, there's some other, I mean we have to
do streets we're being, we have to develop SOPs, ordinances is a big thing, inspect all over facilities.
So, as Todd had said, we have to inspect all of our outfalls.
There's 39 within the city of Miami, and outfall is where water will convey and enter
into waters of the U.S. whether it be TARC Creek, Quail Creek, Neo-Showed as a matter.
So we have to inspect them manually, and also tell DQ what our results are.
And then there's that complaints.
We had to address that, or if anybody had any concerns.
I don't know a couple of years back we had the news record called us, because a woman
had called and was scared what's happening is everybody can die in Miami because there
was yellow on all the streets everywhere.
So we had to go out, and you literally have to trace it back, and there were places that
it looked like somebody had just dumped yellow, bright yellow paint in some of our outfalls
and stuff like that.
And what it was is we had had a storm, and it was right just prior to pollination.
And so everything exploded off of the trees all at once, and it was just pollen, but it was kind
of a big thing.
So is there any questions?
I'm just kind of curious, it seems like a gigantic task.
Are we fully implementing called the policies, and it is, it's showing violations for people
who are not in compliance with it?
We do have an ordinance ordinance 1537.
We do have the authority to, yeah, I mean if we get, if we notice anybody violating anything
within our stormwater ordinance, we are allowed to go out and inspect, we can do administrative
penalties, civil penalties, criminal penalties, but we have not had to do that.
We have had calls, and we've gone out there, and then you trace it back, and it's totally
fine potable water, or we've issued, you need to clean this up immediately, and we go back
and inspect, and we'd not had to ever go past just talking to the offender.
So.
More questions?
No, okay, thank you very much, we appreciate it.
I have a team, there's nomination to appoint Jordan board to the board, to the Miami
downtown redevelopment of 343-year term ending June of 2019, I think I mentioned the last meeting.
a little bit about Mr. Boyd and he has agreed to serve on the MDI and an empty spot and so I
put forth his name nomination for that spot. I'd like to get a most new program mayor's
nomination of Jordan Boyd. It's a second. Roll call please. Johnson. All right. Fourster. All right.
Lewis. Hi. Weston. All right. Thank you. Item number 19 from all. I'll always
FY 2016-17 municipal budget and resolution regarding city Miami. Oklahoma budget for fiscal year
2016-17 and establishing budget amendment authority. Do you want to start me? I'd be happy to.
I think that on this budget we have a little good news and bad news and I'm going to ask Joe
to go to detail on we do have our insurance quotes that come in at this time of the year. I think
this is something we're going to be working on trying to keep this from happening. Now the good news
is that our property casualty insurance actually came in under what we had anticipated in the budget. So
that really doesn't have anything but a good effect on our budget. But our insurance of course and we're seeing
just nationwide our insurance rates went up significant health insurance exactly and I'm going to ask
Jill to kind of go over how much they went up over what was in our prepared budget and how we're dealing
with that and this would be part of your budget approval tonight if you agreed with what we're doing.
Other than that we've made no changes in the budget that we have discussed we're pretty much ready to
go especially with the work plan that we're outlining unless you have any additional changes or questions
at this time but I think these are probably the biggest changes to the budget since the last time we
talked about it and I'll let Jill and Lindsay go into the detail at this time if it's okay.
So $319,000 and some change I can use $390 are what we budgeted and then our numbers that came in we were
under budgeted by $319,000. So what we're proposing to do is take the money from a rainy day
transfer so we were going to transfer money over from the MSUA to the rainy day so instead of doing that
we wanted to we've got a proposed to put $319,000 to our health insurance fund it's called the insurance
fund but it is for health insurances and reduce the amount to the rainy day so that would reduce the rainy day
transfer from MSUA to $166 for one year for one year yeah if we as for what's proposed is to take
$2 million out of the rainy day fund to rehab this building and make it more where the public is kind
of put in one area so we know who's in the building at one time it's really a safety issue for everybody
because if we ever had an event we wouldn't know exactly where everybody is at all times.
So that's very important, but if we take the 2 million out, we had proposed for the next seven
years to repay the rainy day fund.
So the first payment, which would be 1617 would only be 166 because we took 319 and took
it over to the health insurance fund.
The remaining six years would be a $305,000 transfer to the rainy day to make up the difference
for that 2 million.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Which are original amount we had, but we had put in there was 286, so it only increased
about 20,000 over the next for six years.
Yeah.
So the other side of the market is just going to be less the first year.
The first year.
What kind of balance is that?
Leave it for any day.
Up 4 million?
At the end of this year, at the end of 630, if 17, it'll be 4,458 and 750.
And that's assuming we take the entire 2 million properly as we go into that process.
I don't think we would be drawing as much.
We probably would be working with the design bill contractor and going into it on a gradual
basis.
So in other words, we're not going to be taking 2 million out of medium.
Correct.
As needed, only.
I would like to point out on health insurance.
You'll remember that we made a decision to hire NFP as a broker.
And what I'm recommending is doing this this year, but what we have to do and what the reason
we hired the brokers, we have to actively manage our health insurance.
We've not been doing that.
We have a number of different proposals that NFP is both said to get us through this
home right now, what we're doing is budgeting to what's called expected claims.
NFP is also asking us to go into something that we've not had before, and that's aggregate
insurance.
In other words, in the past when we've self-funded, there was always a possibility of having claims
that could far exceed the amount of money that we budget.
Now, by this, by doing what we're talking about making it for 319,000, that is budgeting
to expect claims.
Now, there's still where the aggregate insurance will come in, is still about a gap of 400,000
roughly.
But before we had no gap whatsoever, it could be a million or more under our self-funded plan.
So already NFP is making recommendations to us not only to be able to understand exactly where
we would be.
In case we had some very large health insurance claims, and we all know that you can get in,
but also to start actively managing.
Active management means that we would have more basically preferred providers where, for
such, some types of insurance, or some types of procedures, there would be a preferred provider
that we would have people go to, or else they would make larger claims.
We're going to have to look at what employees pay.
There's no two ways about it.
We're going to have to look at different programs, wellness programs, to try to keep people
from getting sick, in other words.
So this is probably the last year that we're going to be coming in and saying, well, we had more
money we had.
more experience, health insurance costs are going up. We've got to actively manage it.
Otherwise, it's going to get out of control. This is not unusual to my
aim. This is what almost every city in the nation is going through. Anybody that
provides health insurance is going through. In fact, if anything, we're probably a
little late to the party. But one of the important things in doing this is we've
got to work with our employees. This is a major benefit that we provide people. And
if we're going to be making changes in it, we need to let them know what's
going to happen so they can also have plans and also have input as to how we
deal with this. So this is going to be a major activity over the next few months.
We did not anticipate it was going to be as high as it was, but I think even with
Senator Lankford was here last week, he indicated how much health insurance is
gone up all over the place. So it's just our way of having to deal with it. But we have to take
a better control of it and we're in that process.
Okay. Questions are really the only difference between the budget as we've looked at
the last couple of times is this change and adjustment to cover our 319 shortfall and the
payback time. Payback period would be a little bit different to your house.
If there are no questions, do we have a motion to approve?
I'll make a motion to approve. Second.
Second. Roll call, please.
Question?
Aye.
Johnson?
Forster? Aye.
Lewis?
Aye.
Shelds.
Thank you. And thank you ladies for your hard work and HR department also.
I'm 20 out of new business. Any new business?
Okay. Mayor and Council committee announcements. Any announcements?
One mayor.
Send a clock. No, you went and saw a point for a national championship.
Awesome.
What's school?
Well, I don't know where everyone's shirt. I haven't.
I don't put all over what shoes national championships don't sure to come back going.
I don't know.
This is on record. I could be held against me.
Is this city manager having any communication?
Actually, two very good things.
Number one, I think of the last meeting we finished tonight said that it was just before there was going to be a vote by Opa on Route 66 landing.
And Route 66, it was recommended by staff and it was approved by the board.
So we now have that program in which we're looking at in the courier of town about 17 single family homes.
We'll transfer properties from the county and make that available.
Working with them right now on parking in the area where these people can park.
And I think it's just a positive all the way around.
the single family homes would remember what I call the Robinson building or but people know the harvest time
that's going to be converted into loft apartments for seniors which means 55 and older so a lot of
us around this table could live there if they want to. But anyway that's great news and I think everybody
that was involved with us, everybody it helped, they deserve our things because this could be the
start of something very good for my and that was something we needed. The second very good thing is we
got word on the splash pad we have been granted the splash pad grant and as I put out to staff
it's 39 seconds of celebration and then a lot of hard work because we have two state agencies involved
one is ODEQ because the identified area, the Department of Tourism which gave us the grant,
is well aware that we're talking about it at the Eagle picture poverty but also that they have a
relatively tight time frame and right now working with ODEQ they're indicating that they may not
be able to demolish the building until right after the first of the year. So our job right now is to make
sure that we can mesh the timing of the demolition of the building and the timing that we have of the splash
pad. We're going to have to be working on that very closely right away. We believe in that area that
for some reason we can't mesh that right now we might have some other areas in our land that we own
in the park in the Joe Pollock field area where the splash pad can go in. In other words we're going to have a
splash pad in my end of that. No way it's answered but that was another very good news and I know a lot of
people in public works and parks worked very very hard on this one and it's something that I think once this
all said and done is going to be great for our kids so two good news items so I'm going to end it that.
Awesome thank you. I am 23 as a German we have a motion to adjourn.
I have a second.